Volcanic
eruptions,
earthquakes.
Tidal waves,
hurricanes,
floods—our blue planet is shaken by natural disasters that disrupt both the environment and the living world.
As climate change increases,
the damage inflicted by these violent events is ever more frequent and dangerous.
It's urgent that we understand the nature of natural disasters,
in order to anticipate them and give exposed populations time to take shelter.
In recent years,
science has progressed at lightning speed,
and recent discoveries help us to see the Earth differently than we have in the past.
For a long time,
each cataclysm was considered an isolated phenomenon,
a random accident.
Today,
scientists are discovering the links that exist between these phenomena.
They have shown.
That the eruption of a volcano impacts the oceans,
typhoons can cause earthquakes.
Melting ice can awaken dormant volcanoes.
Whenever the balance of the Earth threatens to break down,
natural disasters intervene.
Together,
as regulators,
they are brutal and dangerous for man.
But,
they also reflect the life of the Earth,
its breathing,
its palpitations,
its heartbeat.
Penetrating the fascinating complexity of these natural disasters leads us into the intimacy of our blue planet.
This is the Earth as we have never seen it before.
C'est juste une grande émotion d'être dans cette grotte.
Il faut imaginer que cette grotte,
il y a plus de des dizaines de milliers d'années,
était une zone où les chasseurs-cueilleurs venaient dessiner,
graver leur conception du monde.
Il y a toujours quelque chose de magique d'être en face de ces peintures.
The Chauvet Cave is one of the most beautiful painted caves discovered to date.
For thousands of years,
by torchlight,
men close to the sapiens,
Aurignacians,
painted strikingly beautiful scenes.
Nothing is left to chance.
Every sign speaks.
Some of these works intrigue the geochemist Sebastian Nomad.
They could be the first representations of a natural disaster in the history of humanity.
All throughout our journey to arrive here,
we are at about 300 meters from the entrance of the Grotte
Chauvet. We have seen many animals.
Mais dans cette grotte,
il y a bien d'autres choses que ces animaux.
Il y a aussi des signes,
des signes intangibles dont on ne connaît pas l'origine.
Et en particulier,
devant nous,
un signe en gerbe,
qui a été gravé,
qui a été fait avec les mains et qui se disjoigne en s'éloignant de la paroi,
comme s'il y avait un jaillissement qui se faisait depuis l'intérieur de la paroi jusqu'à l'extérieur.
These signs are not anodyne,
since we find them four times in the cave,
at four strategic places.
And there is a question that obsesses me:
what is the meaning of these signs of herbs?
We arrive in front of another panel with another herb.
What is exceptional here is that this megalosaurus was drawn with charcoal,
so it is possible to date with carbon-14 this megalosaurus.
It is 36,000 years old.
It is just placed above this herb,
which means that this herb is more than 36,000 years old.
On sait par ailleurs qu'à cette époque,
des volcans à moins de 30 km d'ici étaient aussi en activité.
Cette concordance de temps,
mais cette concordance aussi iconographique,
nous fait penser à une éruption volcanique.
D'ailleurs,
si on prend une photo d'une éruption strombolienne et qu'on la compare à cette gerbe,
où on voit bien ces éléments sortir de terre comme un jaillissement.
From the limestone plateau,
which overlooks the Chauvet cave,
from a distance of nearly 200 meters,
we discover a magnificent panorama of the imposing chain of volcanoes in the Bas Vivarais.
Ashes projected during gigantic eruptions were found at the entrance of the cave.
We know that a certain number of these volcanoes,
among the most important,
are entering eruption exactly at the moment when the Aurignacians occupied the Chauvet cave.
Le spectacle auquel ont dû assister les origanciens était exceptionnel.
Dix-sept volcans ont émis des laves qui ont recouvert des vallées entières sur plusieurs dizaines de kilomètres.
Pour moi,
il n'y a aucun doute qu'ils ont voulu laisser une trace avec les gerbes qu'on peut voir à l'intérieur de la grotte Chauvet et peut-être leur manière de nous transmettre toutes ces émotions qu'ils ont pu avoir à travers les temps.
According to Sebastian Nomad's hypothesis,
the white plumes drawn on the walls of the Chauvet Cave could mark the beginning of the fascinating relationships that have been woven over the years between the history of man and the history of natural disasters.
Violent natural events have always haunted humans.
In the past,
they were considered divine wraths,
heavenly punishments.
But
From the 17th century onwards,
the earth sciences developed at a staggering rate.
Explanations that were rational began to replace those that were religious.
Today,
scientists continually scan the sky and probe the earth,
examining it from every angle to understand how natural disasters occur and how to prevent them from turning into disasters for humans.
Space observation,
as well as a host of recently developed disciplines,
have made astonishing discoveries possible.
Who would suspect that the Mediterranean Sea is the result of a series of large-scale natural disasters?
An enigma that has fascinated generations of scientists for years.
Daniel Garcia Castellanos has been investigating the extraordinary and violent destiny of this sea,
which has generated so many civilizations.
The researcher is convinced that the Strait of Gibraltar is one of the keys to the eventful history of the Mediterranean.
Mirá,
para un geofísico como yo,
el Estrecho de Gibraltar es realmente apasionante.
Es un lugar único.
Es como una singularidad geográfica,
¿no?
Porque es el lugar exacto donde confluyen las aguas del Mediterráneo y del Atlántico.
Y es el lugar que separa el continente africano del europeo.
Y a la vez es el lugar donde convergen las placas tectónicas africana y euroasiática.
Cada año se acercan del orden de cuatro milímetros.
Lo que es interesante es que las estructuras geológicas,
si os fijáis,
el tipo de roca que hay en
Jebel Musa y en la roca de Gibraltar son muy parecidas.
Entonces hay una continuidad en todas las formaciones geológicas del lado africano al lado español,
y esto sugiere que fue el mismo proceso el que formó todas estas formaciones.
In
a distant period,
long before the Oregonians painted volcanic eruptions on the walls of the Chauvet Cave,
the Gibraltar Lock closed.
There are various indications that the Mediterranean basin was almost completely dry.
To find out more,
a geological exploration of the sea floor was launched at the end of the last century.
In 1983,
the American scientific ship Glomar Challenger carried out drillings to a depth of 1,300 meters.
Examining the extracted cores,
the scientists came across a huge layer of salt,
three kilometers thick in some places.
This layer alone represents 10 percent of the salt dissolved in all the world's oceans.
From then on,
the scientists knew they were on the right track.
To describe the events of the natural disaster that made the Mediterranean Sea disappear,
Daniel Garcia Castiñanos has designed a very original collaboration with the animation team from In the Box Animation Studio.
What do you think should be more like this or like this?
Look,
this this is perfect for the Rock of Gibraltar.
Okay.
Based on data provided by the Spanish researcher and the scientific community,
the studio artists reconstruct past events.
This straight here is important.
If you could make it last a bit longer,
something maybe a little bit wider.
Exactly.
Okay,
like this.
Exactly.
Wow.
Oh,
you can edit it like that.
Yeah.
El consenso hoy en día es que hace unos seis millones de años,
aproximación entre las placas tectónicas de Europa y África,
produjo el cierre de los estrechos que conectaban el Atlántico y el Mediterráneo.
Una hipótesis que estudiamos con bastante fuerza es que el nivel del Mediterráneo cayera por más de un kilómetro.
Because it was cut off from the immense reservoir of the world's oceans.
Because it was less and less fed by the rivers that flow into its basin,
and because it was subject to influence of a very hot and dry climate six million years ago,
the Mediterranean Sea evaporated.
A colossal quantity of its water evaporated into the atmosphere.
The salt was then concentrated in the remaining pockets of water in the faults and deep valleys.
Elsewhere,
it crystallized,
and vast white deserts were formed,
covering the whole dried basin.
Este escenario supondría un cambio medioambiental enorme,
porque lo pondría en una situación comparable al actual Mar Muerto,
un mar prácticamente sin vida y con unas condiciones climáticas muy diferentes a las normales.
In the region of Almería,
at the foot of the Sierra Cabrera,
about thirty kilometers from the coast,
a salt formation dating from the Dry Mediterranean Era is visible.
The site represents an exceptional field of investigation for scientists.
It exposes the bottom of the ancient sea,
which,
by the movement of plate tectonics,
has risen to the surface.
This is salt common.
Es la sal que estamos habituados a utilizar para cocinar.
Es la sal que se deposita en el fondo del mar cuando evaporamos agua del mar.
Pero por cada diez partes de sal normal que se acumula en el fondo del mar al evaporarla,
precipitamos una parte de sal como esta.
Esto es yeso.
Esto es lo mismo que tenemos detrás nuestro.
Todo esto que hay detrás son montañas y montañas de yeso,
y todo esto ocurrió en tan solo 20.000 años,
que es nada.
Some distance away,
in the deep bed.
Of the River Aguas,
the Sorbas Cave provides access to the largest underground complex in Spain.
Wow,
qué pasada,
qué bonito.
Here,
the history of the evaporation of the Mediterranean is clearly visible.
Wow.
Impressive.
It's more grand than I thought.
Wow!
Look at this.
What happened?
Wow!
It's all plaster.
All pure crystal plaster.
I've never seen this.
What happened?
Es mucho más profundo.
¿Hasta dónde llega?
Tiene un kilómetro cien metros.
Qué maravilla.
Mira,
se ven las las máclas apuntando hacia arriba.
Ostia,
esta esta es una.
Mira,
mira,
aquí.
También otra característica de la de la cristalización del yeso es que se va curvando conforme va creciendo.
Los cristales se van curvando como si fueran espadas o sables,
sables.
Dani,
quiero enseñarte una cosa.
Mira,
mire.
Vale.
Oh,
anda.
Ah,
mira,
contrafuerte.
Sí,
señor.
Oh,
pues esto estaba claramente bajo bajo el agua,
¿no?
Cuando percibí todo este yeso,
muy bonito.
Ajá,
mira,
aquí aquí se ve muy bien.
Esto es el el centro de nucleación de los cristales.
Van a partir de este punto,
van empiezan a crecer lateralmente en forma de cruz y acaban
Ocupando a partir de estos conos van formando toda esta montaña de yeso que tenemos encima.
Y aquí nos podemos imaginar hace seis millones de años los pescados felizmente nadando las conchas,
hasta que toda esta región es levantada por la fuerza de las plagas tectónicas emerge por encima del mar y es gracias a eso que podemos ver ahora mismo estos maravillosos cristales.
Fantástico.
We now know that the evaporation of the Mediterranean Sea took place in an extraordinarily short time on the geological scale.
But what makes it similar to a large-scale natural disaster is the chain of extreme events that it triggered.
Lo que detectamos también es un aumento de la frecuencia de actividad volcánica.
Rock
samples have identified 13 volcanic eruptions during the period when the Mediterranean was no longer water.
Esto qué significa?
Significa que algo descomprimió las cámaras magmáticas,
y la descompresión estaría ligada a esta evaporación del Mar Mediterráneo.
Al faltar la columna de agua,
la presión en la corteza,
en la que están las cámaras magmáticas,
disminuye,
y esto favorece la expulsión de magma hacia la superficie.
Wow.
The tormented history of the Mediterranean Sea is about to reach its climax.
A breach first occurred in the Gibraltar Lock,
probably as a result of a local earthquake or simply due to natural soil erosion.
The Atlantic then began to flow.
Into the basin.
Slowly at first,
the lock then disintegrated rapidly.
The water rushed in with an unprecedented violence.
We have no other example of this in the history of our planet.
An avalanche with a power equivalent to 120,000 times the flow of the Rhone was produced.
By filling the empty basin,
the ocean must have fallen by 10 meters in a few months,
which indicates the extent of the natural disaster.
Finalmente,
esto tiene como consecuencia que se restablecen las condiciones marinas normales en el Mar Mediterráneo.
Lo que hace es todo este fenómeno resetea o reinicia toda la actividad biológica,
toda la población de especies marinas en el mar Mediterráneo que ahora son importadas del Atlántico porque en lo que en lo que fue el Mediterráneo desecado prácticamente no sobrevivió ninguna especie.
Contemplating the coasts of the Mediterranean today,
who could imagine that this sea has experienced a series of episodes of such violence?
What seems inconceivable and disproportionate for man is often only one event in the span of the Earth's life.
Events such as the rapid replenishment of water in the Mediterranean basin in just a few weeks reveal the processes at work in our planet.
Natural disasters are not isolated,
autonomous phenomena.
They are connected,
and one is often the consequence of another.
Everything is linked.
Looking at the mountains,
the plains,
the reliefs that surround us,
it is hard to imagine that the Earth's crust is a thin,
fragile shell whose pieces are constantly shifting and readjusting.
According to the forces that are exerted on it,
thus volcanism has a considerable influence on the Earth's life.
In the spring of 1991,
Pinatubo,
a volcano that had been dormant for 500 years,
awoke on the island of Luzon.
The authorities proceeded to an emergency evacuation of the population.
On June fifteenth,
one of the largest volcanic eruptions of modern times began.
For nine hours,
in titanic explosions,
Pinatubo spit lava blocks and burning clouds,
triggering mudflow.
A night of ashes fell on the region,
and nearly 300 people died.
Huge quantities of particles were ejected into the atmosphere.
They remained suspended all around the planet for nearly three years.
The column of dust and gas rose to a height of 35 kilometers,
well above the
10-kilometer cruising altitude of airplanes.
Suspended particles obscured the sunlight,
and the average temperature of the Earth dropped significantly.
Scientists discovered the full extent of the consequences of this cooling
30 years later.
They have just demonstrated that a volcanic eruption as powerful as that of Pinatubo has a major impact on the circulation.
Alors,
ce lieu,
déjà,
il est magnifique.
C'est justement une source d'inspiration.
C'est une source de méditation.
C'est en lien très fort avec mon travail,
ma vocation.
On a ici l'océan,
l'océan Atlantique,
qui est mon sujet de recherche principal.
Et je me suis intéressé en particulier aux courants marins.
Je suis fasciné par la dynamique de l'océan à grande échelle,
c'est-à-dire au-delà de l'horizon.
Je m'intéresse à quelle est la dynamique de ces courants,
quels sont les équilibres,
les déséquilibres qu'ils pourraient subir dans le futur,
bien entendu,
mais également dans le passé pour vraiment saisir toute l'étendue de leur dynamique.
Et puis,
en particulier ces dernières années,
je me suis intéressé à une thématique un peu étonnante qui concerne l'effet des éruptions volcaniques sur ces courants marins.
We know that ocean currents are powerful climate regulators.
Didier Swinogado has designed a very simple experiment that reproduces the circulation of the most famous of all of them,
the Gulf Stream.
Je trace en rouge les eaux tropicales.
Pour obtenir des masses d'eau polaires,
je vais utiliser ce pan de glace.
Ce colorant bleu marque le mouvement des eaux polaires.
Ces masses d'eau polaires plongent en profondeur.
Qui ne sont plus lourdes car plus froides que les eaux du fond.
Donc,
nous voyons très bien ici les masses d'eau tropicale rouge qui vont se diriger lentement au niveau des pôles représentés ici par ces masses de glaçons.
Et au contact des glaçons,
elles vont se refroidir et donc devenir plus denses.
En devenant plus denses,
elles vont plonger en profondeur à leur tour et créer une circulation de retournement qui va ensuite faire une boucle avec petit à petit des remontées des eaux des profondeurs vers la surface.
The oceans absorb nearly 90 percent of the atmospheric heat.
The ocean currents,
which circulate in a loop,
redistribute this heat from the tropical regions to the poles.
This redistribution is vital for the Earth's climate and has a decisive influence on plant,
animal,
and human life.
Until recently,
we hadn't made the link between a giant volcanic eruption and the thermal balance of the oceans.
À l'aide de nos simulations numériques,
nous avons pu montrer que peut-être jusqu'à la moitié des variations de la circulation océanique en Atlantique Nord pourrait être liée à cet impact des éruptions volcaniques sur la circulation.
This is what the natural disaster eruption of Pinatubo has taught us.
The ash and sulfate particles projected into the upper layers of the atmosphere circulated around the globe for about three years.
During this period,
the average temperature on the surface of the planet decreased significantly.
As a result,
in the far north,
the amount of cold water that sank to the bottom increased,
and mechanically,
the current became faster.
So much so that about 15 years after the eruption of the volcano.
The warm current of the Gulf Stream was then pulled into this acceleration.
This augmentation of the oceanic circulation has for effect,
well,
to bring more heat to the latitudes and to modify,
for example,
the precipitation regimes in the tropics,
and it could explain,
for example,
the great droughts that we have observed in the 1970s and 1980s in Sahel.
The warm Gulf Stream current crossing the Gulf of Mexico.
Generated a greater number of hurricanes over a period of 15 to 25 years after the volcano erupted.
Then,
little by little,
the rhythm of the current slowed,
and the cycle was reversed to return to normal.
Thus,
the effect of an eruption volcanic can affect the ocean circulation on time scales that can be superior to 30 years,
and this is not nothing.
The simulations by Didiar Swindados team confirm the important role volcanoes play in the climate.
They show the extent to which our Earth is a living organism,
whose different components,
such as its water,
its fiery core,
and its atmosphere.
Are constantly interacting.
Although it seems familiar to us,
the sky remains a territory that is largely unknown.
Scientists are exploring it with passion and determination.
Recently,
they have discovered that colossal quantities of water vapor navigate in the air and constitute serious motors.
For natural disasters,
they are called atmospheric rivers.
Atmospheric rivers avoided detection and for a long time because they're composed of wind,
which in some senses is hard to see in the atmosphere,
and also water vapor,
which is also hard to see,
as opposed to clouds or precipitation,
which are readily visible in the atmosphere.
I'm Duane Walliser,
and I work at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena,
California.
And my interest is in understanding climate,
weather,
and in particular their extremes.
So,
atmospheric rivers were discovered in the early
'90s.
Was an exciting time in atmospheric science.
It's when there was a convergence of a lot of computer power,
a lot of new information from Earth observing satellites.
And it wasn't until we had really nice images from satellite of microwaves that can detect water vapor in the atmosphere that you could start to see actual movement of water vapor.
In the sky,
at low altitude,
researchers have detected huge currents carrying water vapor.
Unlike clouds,
which are composed of suspended droplets,
these air currents circulate over thousands of kilometers and carry a colossal quantity of steam,
comparable to 20 times the volume of the Amazon River.
Where they coined this term,
atmospheric river,
because they transported so much water in the atmosphere across the Great Basin.
This loud,
artificial,
and somewhat annoying sound is part of the instrumentation here to measure atmospheric rivers.
It uses a combination of acoustic waves and electromagnetic waves to measure the strength of the wind speed,
and it also provides a measure of how much water vapor is in the atmosphere.
And the two combine are the ingredients that form an atmospheric river.
Unfortunately,
it's only on for about five minutes every hour,
and returns one data point to the scientists and weather forecasters once every hour.
The data that come from the observatory here is useful in a couple respects.
One is it is used in weather forecasting to help it predict what's going to happen in the next 12,
24,
or a couple days,
and also it gives a present measurement of the extremity of the atmospheric river condition that can then be used locally,
maybe in a near-term warning.
Atmospheric rivers originate in the intertropical zone,
where solar radiation is intense.
The ocean waters evaporate and rise into the sky.
Still at low altitude,
they are taken over by winds that rush in long,
narrow corridors towards temperate zones.
When these winds,
loaded with water vapor,
hit a surface,
they rise to pass the obstacle.
At higher altitudes,
the air is colder.
The water vapor condenses.
The droplets form clouds,
which produce snow or rain.
Some atmospheric rivers,
highly charged with steam,
pour down waterspouts that cause devastating floods for inhabited areas.
In fact,
90%
of the floods that occur on the west coast of the U.S.
are in association with landfalling atmospheric rivers.
We also have strong winds associated with them.
So when they make landfall in areas where people live,
you can get wind damage as well from these extreme storm conditions.
Thanks to the analysis of the meteorological data of the time,
scientists now attribute many of the catastrophic floods of the past to powerful atmospheric rivers,
like the one that ravaged Northern California and,
in particular,
the city of Sacramento in 1930.
In some regions of the globe,
atmospheric rivers have a beneficial impact,
not just those hazardous impacts.
For example,
they're responsible for the delivering the fresh water to the given region.
in Southern California,
about
Ten to twelve storms can be responsible for up to forty to fifty percent of our freshwater supply.
Important for the agriculture in the region,
or just drinking water.
So they have this dual face to them,
both hazard and benefit.
And that's why scientists,
weather forecasters,
climatologists are very interested in atmospheric rivers for both of those reasons.
Projections show that in the future,
the Earth and the atmosphere will become warmer if the air.
Is warmer,
it will absorb more water vapor.
We can therefore assume that atmospheric rivers will become more frequent and more intense in the future.
Any given region that experiences them now is likely to anticipate increases on the order of 10 to 30 to 40 percent in the future.
Now we're talking about
30 to 60 years in the future.
Natural hazards tend to tell us somewhat about the extremes by which the Earth behaves,
or our local environment behaves.
And in the case of atmospheric rivers,
when there's too few of them,
typically experience a drought.
When there's too many of them,
we will experience flooding conditions.
And in some ways,
they show us how to regularize our life around those extreme conditions.
So they're really indicators that tell us something about how to maintain a regularity for society.
Ever-growing in efficiency and number,
measuring stations allow scientists to follow the atmospheric rivers in tropical and temperate zones.
Weather forecasts benefit from this and are becoming more and more accurate.
The exploration and inventory of atmospheric rivers continues,
and scientists are now focused on the Antarctic continent.
In February 2017,
the British Antarctic Survey,
a British research center,
filmed a disturbing crack in the vast ice shelf along the east coast of the Antarctic Peninsula.
The crack stretched over 100 kilometers and was 350 meters deep.
Six months later,
the calving,
as we call the formation of an iceberg,
Created the A68,
one of the largest icebergs observed to date.
The ice sheet that drifted into the Weddell Sea is huge,
big enough to house twice the city of New York.
Do the colossal dimensions of A68 suggest that the polar ice cap will soon disappear?
Its migration is surveyed night and day by observation satellites.
Vincent
Favire comes from a mountain village.
During his childhood,
he saw the glaciers shrink and retreat in the valleys.
Naturally,
during his studies,
he turned to glaciology.
He now works on the retreat of ice around the world,
and particularly in Antarctica.
Je suis très ému par ma présence ici parce que je me trouve dans un site qui est très différent de là où j'ai l'habitude d'aller,
et je me trouve face à un satellite qui sera fondamental pour évaluer l'évolution future du niveau des mers.
Or aujourd'hui,
la grande question qui se pose,
c'est de savoir si l'Antarctique va se désintégrer ou pas.
Le réchauffement climatique contribue à accélérer la fonte en surface des glaciers,
mais aussi à larguer plus d'icebergs vers les océans,
ce qui a un impact sur l'augmentation du niveau des mers.
Il faut bien voir que l'Antarctique est un stock de glace phénoménal.
Si l'ensemble des glaces de l'Antarctique se mettait à fondre,
le niveau des mers augmenterait de 56 mètres.
The Antarctic continent is now the subject of intense observation.
The latest generation of satellites and their advanced equipment are constantly being developed to enhance data collection.
And,
faced with the urgency of climate change,
Americans and Europeans are working together to build an exceptionally accurate measurement tool.
Ah,
ça y est,
c'est bientôt grand jour.
Oui,
on est prêt.
Le satellite est terminé.
On va l'impacter bientôt pour l'emmener à Vandenberg,
en Californie,
pour le lancer sur la fusée Falcon 9 en le dynamo.
Novembre,
il sera bientôt donc à plus de 1000 km.
Oui,
donc le satellite est à peu près à 1360 km,
et de là-haut,
on va mesurer de manière très précise le niveau des océans.
D'accord,
c'est avec ce radar là que ça mesure.
Oui,
donc l'instrument principal c'est le radar qui mesure la distance entre le satellite et la surface des océans,
et son instrument compagnon,
le radiomètre,
permet de corriger les mesures en déterminant la quantité
Les données sont produites dans le programme Copernicus de l'Union européenne,
et qui fournit de manière libre et gratuite toutes les données produites aux scientifiques et à la société civile pour des applications de recherche ou des applications opérationnelles.
Il y a un capteur qui m'intéresse particulièrement,
c'est le radiomètre,
puisque vous m'avez dit que ça ça permet de évaluer la quantité d'humidité dans l'atmosphère.
Et je travaille beaucoup sur ces sur ces données,
sur les processus atmosphériques qui peuvent toucher l'antarctique.
The White Continent is one of the regions of the world that is suffering the most from the melting of the ice.
It is now six times greater than it was 50 years ago,
and threatens a large number of coastal cities in the world.
According to Vincent Favre,
atmospheric rivers play an important role in the rapid acceleration of the Antarctic melt.
We knew for a long time that the surface melting of these ice sheets caused their disintegration,
but the origin of these melting phenomena remained a mystery.
Au cours des douze dernières années,
je suis parti dix fois sur le terrain en Antarctique sur des longues périodes de trois mois,
ce qui m'a permis d'observer longuement les phénomènes atmosphériques.
Je laisse donc ma famille,
mes enfants pour partir dans des conditions relativement extrêmes.
On se retrouve avec des vents de plus de 100 km/h avec de la neige qui soufflait.
Pour effectuer mes mesures sur des centaines de kilomètres,
nous prenons des caravanes,
des tracteurs,
et j'effectue des mesures tous les un à deux kilomètres avec des balises que l'on installe pour mesurer l'accumulation de neige,
mais aussi en effectuant des carottages.
25 mètres 50.
J'installe aussi des stations météorologiques qui nous permettent de suivre l'évolution des conditions météorologiques d'une année sur l'autre.
Et dans ce milieu qui est extrêmement froid,
il nous est arrivé de constater des périodes de fonte.
On January 31,
2013,
at the French scientific base Dumont d'Urville in Terre Adelie,
Vincent Favre witnessed an event he had never seen before.
The temperature suddenly rose to five degrees above zero,
and torrential rains fell without interruption for two whole days.
This rain had been observed up to 1,500 meters altitude,
a thing we had never observed before.
This event has strongly concerned us,
because the rain fell on young poussins whose duvet was not waterproof.
A wet duvet is like a wet doudou; it is no longer insulating.
So the entire 20,000 poussins are freezing to death,
and we have remained to watch this in a totally powerless way.
En 2014,
one of our colleagues published an article.
This article presented in what measure the atmospheric rivers brought enormous heat and precipitation to Antarctica.
So we have extended our research,
and we have been able to show that the entire melting on the
Antarctic of the West and on the platforms was associated with atmospheric rivers.
Since the 2013 environmental disaster,
observations have confirmed that when an atmospheric river flies over Antarctica,
it brings moisture that results in very heavy snowfall.
These bad weather conditions affect the White Continent only five to ten days a year,
and in this short period of time,
they cause all of the annual snowfall.
Thus,
ensuring the renewal of the ice stock.
However,
some rivers,
more powerful than others,
are also warmer.
These rivers accelerate the melting and increase the risk of disintegration.
Integration of the ice shelves,
threatening the lives of many species.
The state of the planet today results from billions of years of life,
and therefore results in an equilibrium.
The cataclysms have played a role in this equilibrium.
The problem is that today,
the cataclysms that can occur risk impacting humankind,
and that is philosophically preoccupying.
Science is
making it possible to better understand the processes involved in the appearance of natural disasters,
and if,
as scientists believe.
Atmospheric rivers are multiplying as a result of climate change.
The Antarctic continent could be turned upside down.
Once again,
we are discovering the role that volcanoes could play in this scenario.
Antarctica is not the only kingdom of ice.
It is also the realm of fire,
as the spectacular eruptions of Mount Erebus in the center of Ross Island remind us.
We know the surface of Mars better than we know the base of the Antarctic ice sheet.
And when I was starting in research,
I really wanted to be working on something new that wasn't already being looked at by a lot of people.
So,
together with some colleagues,
we decided to start looking into volcanism in Antarctica.
Interestingly,
one of the best places to come to actually understand Antarctic volcanism is the other side of the globe,
here in Iceland.
Max Van Wyck Devry,
a doctoral student in geology and glaciology at the University of Minnesota,
USA,
is a precocious talent.
At the age of 24,
the young British scientist has made a series of important discoveries that force us to reconsider the Antarctic problem.
There's still some small glaciers here in Iceland today.
But during the last ice age,
about 10,000 years ago,
the entire island was covered by more than a kilometre of ice—a thick ice sheet,
fairly similar to Antarctica today,
that was about three to four Eiffel towers thick,
so really covering all of the landscape.
So all of the volcanoes which we can see today were entirely buried beneath this ice sheet.
So we can come here,
and we can look at the processes that are happening today,
and better understand what's going on in Antarctica.
Glaciation and volcanism are the two processes that have really shaped Iceland as the island that we know today.
Katla volcano is an excellent example of this,
because to this day the volcano is still entirely covered by a glacier,
named Myrdalsjökull,
which we can see a piece of right here.
And if you look closely at this glacier right here,
you can also see a number of dark bands throughout it.
And what these dark bands are formed of is layers of volcanic ash from past eruptions of Katla.
Now scientists can actually analyze each of these bands to understand the timing and the nature of past eruptions of Katla.
A layer of ice,
400 meters thick,
covers the crater of Katla.
The volcano erupts once or twice a century,
on average.
The mechanism that is at work during its activity illustrates what can happen in.
Antarctica.
The weight of the ice exerts a strong pressure on the Earth's crust.
This pressure prevents the magma from rising to the surface.
But if the ice on the surface melts,
then the pressure on the Earth's crust is relieved.
Consequently,
the magma manages to go up.
At its contact,
the ice melts.
Lakes and rivers are formed.
Their warm waters further accelerate the melting of the cap from below,
which favors new upwelling of magma.
An eruption eventually breaks through the cap.
It spreads black ash,
which captures the heat of the sun instead of reflecting it.
A vicious circle is thus set in motion.
So we have two things happening.
Putting this together.
Can make a cycle in which increased eruptions thin the ice faster,
and more rapid thinning of the glaciers actually increases the number of eruptions.
Katla is one of Iceland's most active and most dangerous volcanoes,
because it sends floods washing down the surrounding landscape.
The immense dark plains of ground,
which stretch infinitely out from the glacier,
are the stigmata of the devastations generated by violent floods.
The Icelanders call them jökulhups.
They are the result of the brutal flow of the enormous pockets of water accumulated under the ice following a volcanic eruption.
Their overflow is as powerful as a dam breaking.
It sweeps away everything in its path.
A flood loaded with ash inundates the region and shakes it,
as a tsunami would,
leaving behind desolate regions.
These subglacial eruptions have been common in Iceland's history,
including at the end of the last ice age,
when the entire country was covered by a large ice sheet.
And a similar situation could occur in Antarctica today,
if the volcanoes.
We're active.
I'm standing here on a very young lava flow in Iceland.
This was all erupted only a week ago,
and you can still feel the warmth here,
and you can see all the textures on the surface of the lava from when it was flowing.
And probably looks fairly similar to what a subglacial volcano would at the same age.
While the processes are a little bit different,
here the lava is cooling more slowly,
as it's only in contact with the atmosphere.
Whereas at a subglacial volcano,
the lava would cool much faster,
in contact with either ice or a subglacial lake.
But the volcanoes look fairly similar,
and they're both building up,
stack.
After stack of lavas,
which gradually forms a cone,
and it's exactly these cones that we were looking for,
deep underneath the Antarctic ice sheet.
The work of Max Van Wyck Devries and his colleagues has revealed,
for the first time,
what lies beneath the thick ice cap that covers Antarctica.
Buried under more than two kilometers of ice.
This region of the planet is one of the last that remains inaccessible to humans.
With radars whose rays penetrate the ice,
and by processing countless geophysical and satellite data,
the researchers have located a constellation of volcanic cones,
confirming the observations of traces of ash under the ice.
Located in the west of the continent,
this set of volcanoes constitutes one of the largest volcanic rifts on the planet.
It extends over 2,500 kilometers,
the distance from Paris to Moscow,
in the part of Antarctica most sensitive to climate change.
If these volcanoes become active again,
the consequences could be disastrous.
To our great surprise,
we discovered more than a hundred volcanic cones hidden beneath the Antarctic ice sheet.
The size of these is also surprising; that they range from only a hundred meters tall all the way up to a kilometer and a half,
which is about the same size as all these volcanoes here in Iceland.
And this is really one of the big questions that's remaining for us.
We know the melting of this ice is going to be driven primarily by warming in the atmosphere and the oceans,
but what we don't know is where the volcanoes can,
in some
Specific areas accelerate the rate at which these glaciers melt,
and for Antarctica,
this is very important for all of us,
because melting a small part of the Antarctic ice sheet faster can raise sea levels all around the world.
About 40 percent of the world's population lives within 100 kilometers of the sea.
If the rise in sea level were to reach 50 meters,
which is possible in the event that the white continent were to disintegrate in its entirety,
many highly populated regions could be wiped off the map.
The marine currents would change; the whole climate would be deeply upset.
For the planet.
On its own timescale,
no one knows what new balance would be established after such a catastrophe.
Faced with the accelerating frequency and power of violent natural events,
scientists are mobilizing.
They continue to explore the links between these phenomena and try to respond to the threats they represent.
Located on the Pacific Ring of Fire,
the island of Taiwan,
off the coast of China,
was born from the collision of the Eurasian,
Pacific,
and Philippine tectonic plates.
The island is constantly shaking.
Between 30,000 and 40,000 earthquakes of various intensities are recorded each year.
That is to say,
a thousand per day.
Seismological research is the most advanced in the world.
And for the first time,
scientists are exploring the hypothesis that typhoons trigger earthquakes.
Professor Lin is in charge of the Department of Atmospheric Instrumentation and Measurement at the National University of Taiwan.
With the support of Sophie Laplace,
former pilot and research assistant,
they organize,
in cooperation with the Air Force,
airborne missions in the heart of typhoons to measure various parameters.
Euh,
we today expect this time to be about four or five hours.
That,
because we today if euh forecasted this typhoon radius is correct,
then in the high wind we will face.
If there is a pressure difference,
we will do a emergency descent procedure.
Des risques particuliers,
bien sûr,
puisque le risque zéro n'existe pas.
Il y a toujours possibilité d'être pris dans le typhon si jamais il se met à changer de position très rapidement.
Ces sondes,
elles sont équipées d'appareils météorologiques.
Donc,
il y a un thermomètre pour la température,
l'humidité,
la vitesse du vent,
la direction du vent.
The primary mission of Professor Lin's team is to help the authorities to better understand the strength of typhoons and to keep threatened populations safe.
The measurements
made in Taiwan enrich huge meteorological databases.
These are then processed by supercomputers,
whose computing power has been multiplied by 10 million in 30 years.
These giant machines,
like Joliot-Curie in France,
operate 24 hours a day,
seven days a week,
in a deafening noise.
They allow,
from old observations,
to reconstitute the past climatic conditions and to simulate the future evolutions by taking into account the changing climate.
Aujourd'hui,
la science a changé.
J'appartiens à une nouvelle génération de scientifiques qui utilisons de plus en plus les ordinateurs et la modélisation numérique,
notamment les supercalculateurs,
qui nous permettent d'aborder des problèmes de plus en plus complexes,
d'aborder des problèmes mêlant ce qui se passe dans l'atmosphère,
ce qui se passe à la surface des continents et ce qui se passe au niveau de la croûte terrestre.
Je m'appelle Philippe Ster,
je suis enseignant chercheur à l'université de Rennes 1.
Ma spécialité c'est les sciences de la Terre et notamment l'étude des séismes et de la dynamique des paysages.
Je me suis posé cette question-là :
est-ce que les typhons pouvaient avoir un effet mesurable sur la déformation tectonique ?
Alors,
les outils qu'on a utilisés,
c'est principalement des extenso-mètres,
c'est-à-dire c'est des petits boîtiers en fait qui font à peu près une quinzaine de centimètres de diamètre et qui sont capables de mesurer des déformations vraiment infimes,
c'est-à-dire des déformations plus petites qu'un millionième de la taille du diamètre d'un cheveu.
Et ces extenso-mètres,
en fait,
ils sont placés à peu près à 200 mètres de profondeur et ils vont enregistrer les déformations relativement douces et subtiles que un typhon peut engendrer lorsqu'il va passer au-dessus d'une île comme Taïwan.
Dans notre étude,
nous avons observé à peu près une trentaine de typhons qui ont impacté l'île de Taïwan sur sur une dizaine d'années.
Cela nous a permis en fait d'avoir un grand nombre de données à notre disposition pour comprendre comment un typhon allait justement modifier la déformation tectonique,
et notamment en fonction de la quantité de précipitations qui tombent lors du typhon,
ou en fonction aussi de la dépression atmosphérique qui est engendrée par le typhon.
Alors,
quels sont les mécanismes en fait qui se mettent en place lorsqu'un typhon passe au-dessus de Taïwan ?
il y a deux mécanismes principaux.
D'abord,
un typhon c'est une dépression atmosphérique,
et il va générer comme une aspiration de la surface,
que ce soit des océans ou de la surface des continents,
qu'on peut voir un peu à l'image d'un ressort,
va être tiré vers le haut lors du passage du typhon.
Alors,
ça va générer une remontée de la surface terrestre de quelques millimètres.
Et ensuite,
on va avoir une deuxième phase qui va être une phase plutôt où le ressort va venir se comprimer sous l'effet des précipitations.
En fait,
les précipitations vont s'accumuler dans les nappes alluviales,
vont s'accumuler aussi dans dans les rivières,
et toute cette eau va peser sur la croûte terrestre.
Et donc,
va appuyer sur sur ce ressort,
et donc ce ce mouvement à la fois d'extension puis après de compression,
en fait,
c'est capable après de de rajouter des contraintes à la croûte terrestre,
qui peuvent à terme mener à induire de nouveaux séismes.
Ces résultats participent à à démontrer que les forces tectoniques.
Tectonic are not the only responsible for earthquakes.
We can have,
finally,
other processes,
notably processes like typhoons,
atmospheric processes,
or even erosion processes,
which can,
in fact,
add forces to the faults and potentially trigger earthquakes.
Ce qui m'a frappé avec ces résultats,
c'est qu'on démontre que les séismes et les typhons sont capables de déclencher de très nombreux glissements de terrain,
et ces glissements de terrain vont apporter des quantités phénoménales en fait de sédiments dans les rivières,
ce qui va en fait remodeler totalement à la fois la forme des rivières et la forme des versants en leur redonnant un côté beaucoup plus naturel.
Donc c'est vrai que vu sous cet angle-là,
les séismes,
les typhons et les glissements de terrain en fait contribuent à réguler la forme des paysages.
What happens at the level of the atmosphere,
what happens at the level of the Earth's crust,
and what happens at the surface of the continents—all that is linked.
That is to say,
that processes like typhoons,
earthquakes,
and ground movements can influence each other,
particularly through mechanisms of interaction that were not necessarily obvious to demonstrate.
Philippe Steer's research
offers new evidence of the links between extreme events.
Their sequencing is not neutral.
They participate in the reconfiguration of the landscapes of a geographical area.
They disrupt the ecosystems in place,
and therefore also have a significant impact on the living world.
This is what the history of our Earth teaches us.
In the past,
great natural disasters have changed the distribution of species.
Of the five mass extinctions counted to date,
the best known is that of the dinosaurs,
which occurred sixty-five million years ago.
Every cloud has a silver lining,
since their disappearance gave mammals a chance to develop after their predators had gone extinct.
Are natural disasters a tragedy for the living,
or an opportunity?
Probably both at once.
At the University of Antwerp in Belgium,
researchers have shown that when nature is subjected to a powerful imbalance,
it reshuffles the deck.
To verify this hypothesis,
biologists Anthony Harrell and Sam Wassenberger have devised a surprising experiment.
So this animal is Anolis carolinensis.
It belongs to the same family as Anolis scriptus,
an animal that we worked on the Turks and Caicos Islands,
a group of islands just south of the Bahamas.
And when you look at this lizard,
it looks like just any ordinary lizard,
but in fact it's actually quite extraordinary.
And one of its superpowers is that it can actually resist to hurricanes,
which is quite an amazing feat for just just a small lizard.
So this project started in 2017 when we were in Turks and Caicos to study population of lizards,
anoles lizards,
and we measured the whole population.
We got data for over 100 lizards,
and just three days after we left,
there were two hurricanes that hit the island,
like straight on.
We first had Hurricane Irma,
who hit the island with wind speeds of over 260 kilometers an hour,
and then right after we had Hurricane Maria,
hitting basically again our study island completely.
At first,
we were really devastated because we thought we lost our data.
But then,
while thinking a little bit about it,
we thought this is a unique opportunity to really understand the role of hurricanes as possible agents of natural selection on these populations.
And so,
as soon as we were able to go back,
we went back to the island,
and we measured the lizards again.
And what we saw was really unbelievable,
because we saw that the lizards that had survived the hurricane were morphologically completely different.
From the ones we measured before the hurricane,
which means that certain individuals survived the hurricane and others died.
And so,
what's really interesting,
if if you look at these anolis lizards,
they have these adhesive toe pads.
So these little things that they help them to grip onto leaves and branches.
And these toe pads of the ones that survived the hurricane were much bigger than the
The ones before the hurricane.
The other thing we saw is that the forelimbs of the animals,
of the ones that survived,
were much longer,
which allowed them possibly to adhere better to branches.
But the really strange thing is that the
The hind limbs of the animals that survived the hurricane were actually shorter than what we had measured before,
and so this is really a really unusual feature.
And to understand what really happens,
we needed to do experiments.
So here we have a leaf blower,
and so the leaf blower is going to create hurricane-level winds on the animal that's sitting on the perch.
We have a high-speed camera; it's filming at 500 frames a second,
so we can actually slow down the movement of the animal confronted with the wind.
And then we have some padding behind the lizard to make sure that it doesn't get hurt as it is blown off the perch.
And so the whole point of doing this experiment,
there's two reasons for it.
One is to understand the behavior of the lizard.
So,
when it when it's blowing,
what is it doing?
And then secondly,
it will give us the data to be able to build an aerodynamic model.
Gives us the mechanical interaction between the wind and the lizard and its anatomy.
Sam,
you ready?
Yes.
All right.
Okay,
this is quite interesting.
So we can see that the hind limbs are really detaching from the substrate.
And it comes completely loose.
Yes,
this makes a lot of sense.
In the aerodynamic models that I made,
the highest wind forces are exactly on the hind limbs.
And do you think this means that having longer hind limbs would incur higher forces?
Yeah,
exactly.
Okay.
And so,
if that's true,
then maybe we can understand why natural selection is actually favoring animals with shorter hind limbs.
Because they have less forces and they can probably attach better to the substrate.
Do you think it's true?
Perfect sense.
Okay,
very nice.
Experiments conducted with the beautiful lizards of the Turks and Caicos Islands shows how natural disasters,
in this case hurricanes,
have the power to redefine the evolution of species.
The experiments will be extended to other living organisms to expand the work of Harel and Wassenberg.
Certain natural disasters,
by their magnitude and their repercussions,
become the agents of a massive,
imposed and brutal selection.
However,
more and more clues lead us to believe that they are also at the origin of life on Earth.
In the heart of the massive central,
a lake of volcanic origin.
Bears witness to the fact that the appearance of the first living organisms probably occurred with great violence.
We're going to go to the orange burr orchid over there.
Okay,
very good.
So we'll be at the vertical of 92 meters,
so at the maximum depth of the lake.
And so at the center of the lake,
then,
is that?
Yes.
We're going to make samples at 10 meters,
and we'll try to go into the deep zone,
the zone without oxygen,
beyond 60 meters.
Le lac Pavin,
c'est vraiment un système qui est fascinant,
quelque soit la période de l'année.
En hiver,
il est beaucoup plus sombre,
beaucoup plus obscur,
et un peu plus angoissant parfois.
Et puis quand arrive le printemps ou la nature renaît,
c'est vrai que c'est un endroit qui a un petit havre de paix et de sérénité.
Donc le lac Pavin,
c'est un volcan.
C'est un cratère de mare.
Un cratère de mare,
c'est quoi?
C'est un volcan qui se forme par la rencontre entre du magma et une nappe réattique.
Alors ça crée une violente explosion qui crée un cratère de forme circulaire,
et ce cratère se remplit d'eau et forme un lac.
Faut imaginer ce lac qui fait 92 mètres de profondeur.
Et pourquoi est-ce qu'il est très particulier ?
Parce que c'est comme une superposition de deux lacs.
Il y a une première partie qui va de 0 à 60 mètres qui fonctionne comme un lac classique.
C'est quoi un lac classique?
C'est un lac qui,
dans les régions tempérées comme la nôtre,
va se mélanger une ou deux fois dans l'année.
Vers une ou deux fois dans l'année,
les eaux de surface vont descendre au fond et les eaux du fond vont remonter en surface.
Ça permet de réoxygéner les eaux profondes.
Mais le lac Pavin a cette particularité que le brassage ne s'effectue que sur les 60 premiers mètres.
Et de 60 mètres à 92 mètres,
cette eau n'est jamais mélangée.
Et comme elle n'est jamais mélangée,
elle n'est jamais réoxygénée.
Donc il n'y a jamais d'oxygène.
The samples taken from the water of the lake below 60 meters are surprising.
Anne Catherine Leur and her team counted up to 10 million microorganisms in a single milliliter of water.
Under the electron microscope,
these microorganisms reveal that a wealth of life proliferates in the depth of the pavement.
Why these microorganisms interest me particularly?
Because they are the descendants of the first organisms that colonized the Earth 3 billion years ago.
At the beginning of the period known as the Archean,
only a very small portion of the continental crust had emerged.
The Earth looked a bit like an ocean planet,
and in this very particular environment,
there was no oxygen,
neither in the atmosphere nor in the oceans of primitive Earth.
Et donc,
ce système pavant dans cette zone profonde est un analogue de ces océans Archean.
Alors que les océans contemporains ne présentent plus du tout ces caractéristiques.
Une question qui anime beaucoup les scientifiques,
c'est de comprendre comment la vie a pu apparaître sur Terre.
L'apparition de la vie sur Terre,
c'est pas un événement.
En un claquement de doigts,
la vie n'est pas apparue sur Terre.
C'est un processus.
Et pour que ce processus puisse s'enclencher,
pour que la vie puisse commencer à apparaître,
il a fallu que la Terre primitive présente des conditions favorables.
Alors les conditions favorables,
c'est quoi ?
Bah,
c'est d'avoir de l'eau,
une atmosphère.
D'avoir également des températures compatibles avec l'apparition de la vie,
mais également d'avoir un certain nombre d'éléments réactifs,
d'avoir des éléments qui vont pouvoir s'ajoncer pour former des briques qui vont être les premières briques constitutives du vivant.
Et ces éléments réactifs,
il a fallu qu'ils soient disponibles sur cette Terre primitive.
Et c'est en cela que les volcans jouent un rôle important.
Les volcans émettent,
par exemple,
du CO2,
du dioxyde de carbone.
Vont émettre également un certain nombre d'autres gaz,
comme des gaz contenant du soufre ou alors de l'azote.
Il semblerait,
même si on n'a pas encore de certitude,
que non seulement ils aient pu fournir ces éléments,
mais qu'ils aient pu également fournir des lieux privilégiés pour le développement de cette vie.
Certains scientifiques pensent ainsi.
From the time of the inhabitants of the Chauvet Cave until today,
in the minds of men,
volcanoes are associated with the fear they arose and their destructive power.
We now know that they contributed to the emergence of life on Earth.
Even today,
they favor.
The development of living beings whose faculties of adaptation are unprecedented.
Some of these organisms are sheltered within a volcanic structure,
very close to Lake Paven.
Only teams of scientists are allowed to descend under the guidance of experienced speleologists.
First safety instructions:
no one stays under appeal.
The least time possible.
It's the most dangerous place in the cavity because of the falling blocks.
Bienvenue,
Angela.
The
Susie Hollow is an exceptional natural cavity,
which,
to date,
Has no equivalent.
It is the result of a major volcanic eruption that lasted more than three million years.
The immense layer of lava underwent successive collapses that eventually created an underground void.
This is how the spectacular vault,
30 meters in height,
was born.
Today,
it houses a lake that is still largely unexplored.
All this chain of events.
Ça a permis la mise en place de conditions très particulières.
Par exemple,
c'est l'obscurité.
L'obscurité,
ça interdit la photosynthèse.
Il y a aussi le problème de la température,
qui est très faible,
cinq degrés à peu près dans la salle et 1,8 degré.
C'est aussi un milieu oligotrophe,
c'est-à-dire qu'il n'y a très peu en fait d'éléments nutritifs pour permettre le développement de la vie.
Et pourtant,
eh bien,
des organismes ont réussi quand même à se développer dans ce milieu.
C'est vrai quand on parle de milieux extrêmes,
on pense souvent à des milieux très chauds,
des milieux très salés,
des milieux très acides,
mais des milieux très froids,
très faibles en éléments nutritifs,
ce sont aussi des milieux extrêmes.
Ça nous permet d'étudier des éléments qui nous permettent de repousser les frontières des limites du vivant.
Je vais mettre de l'antibuée dans mon masque.
The mysterious living beings that have managed to adapt to such difficult conditions are hiding in the lake.
Collecting samples requires a dedicated dive.
The very cold temperature of the water does not allow for prolonged exploration.
No,
c'est qui du maximum mon tibo.
Ah oui,
d'accord.
Voilà.
Et bon,
super.
Allez,
ciao.
And to evolve in the labyrinth of dark and flooded galleries,
still partly unexplored,
it is necessary to have significant experience.
The microorganisms of Suse,
which are so precious to scientists,
have the particularity of gathering where a thin ray of light penetrates through the ceiling of the cavity for a few hours a day.
This is the source of energy they need to survive.
They form a strange constellation of orange dust.
Collecting them requires precaution and a great deal of effort.
Ça va ?
Eh ben,
t'es deux,
t'es deux petits pots ont éclaté.
Donc j'ai pu observer que de l'astreinte.
Très bien,
c'est bien.
Désolé.
Ça sera largement suffisant.
Eh ben tant mieux.
On va,
on va en garder un petit peu pour la microscopie électronique et le reste partira aux États-Unis.
C'est une bonne chose.
Merci,
Jean-Michel.
Je vais aller transférer tout de suite.
With this sample,
Anne Catherine Leurre will be able to sequence the genome of the.
Extraordinary organisms of Susi.
She may discover how these mysterious extremophiles have colonized the underground lake,
and how they manage to live in an environment where no other living thing can.
What is fascinating is that volcanoes allow to provide the elements that were necessary for the creation of life.
Finally,
the current volcanoes are always sorts of small bubbles,
vents that will allow the development of a life thriving within ecosystems of extremely rich microorganisms.
In recent decades,
science has made great strides in understanding the complex mechanisms that make our planet hospitable to life.
Thanks to the research undertaken,
cross-referencing the knowledge of many disciplines,
we have discovered that the forces at work on the Earth,
as well as in the sky and in the hearts of oceans,
react with each other and form chains of events that we could not have imagined.
We now know that our planet is a robust organism,
endowed with regulatory systems that allow it to survive severe environmental changes.
We also know that,
like any living organisms,
it has limits,
which,
if crossed,
would endanger the very life it shelters.
These scientific advances provide us with a lesson in humility.
They question our place in a world whose story is unfolding on a timescale much broader than our own.
A world in which man's survival will depend on his ability to understand and adapt to the extraordinary effervescence of the Earth.